William Moomaw Papers MS216
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
William Moomaw Papers
1992 -- 2014
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Moomaw, William
MS216
10.8 Linear Feet 9 boxes
1 Artifact(s)
5 Digital Object(s)
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the papers of William Moomaw. It documents his work as a professor at the Fletcher School, including class materials, lecture notes, and bound research materials.
Biographical / Historical
William Moomaw (born 1938) is professor emeritus of international environmental policy at Tufts University.
Born on February 18, 1938 in Kansas City, Missouri, William Renken Moomaw acquired a BA in chemistry from Williams College in 1959 and his PhD in physical chemistry from MIT in 1965.
He has taught or worked at several institutions, including the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy and Williams College (where he also served as the director of William College's Center for Environmental Studies from 1982-1988). He established the Center for International and Environment and Resource Policy (CIERP) in 1992 and was its director until he retired from this position in 2013. He has directed the Tufts Institute of the Environment and the Tufts Climate Initiative since 1998 and 1999, respectively, and co-directed the Global Development and Environment Institute since 1993. Moomaw's involvement with other programs and organizations includes work with the Center for Ecological Technologies; Clean Air-Cool Planet; The Climate Group; Climate Resource Initiative's Climate, Energy, and Resource program; the Consensus Building Institute; and the Earthwatch Institute.
Professor Moomaw has co-authored numerous works, including four Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) reports and an IPCC book chapter. He also co-authored the 2005 Millennium Ecosystem Assessment on nitrogen and helped the United States Congress develop legislation focusing on energy problems, forestry management, and the elimination of chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs) in spray cans.
Moomaw's awards include a Bicentennial Medal from Williams College; an honorary doctorate of philosophy from Belgarde University; and a 2007 Nobel Peace Prize, which was co-awarded to both the IPCC and Al Gore.
He is married to Margot Moomaw. They reside in Williamstown, Massachusetts.
Environmental policy -- Research; Environmental policy -- International cooperation; Faculty papers; Faculty research; Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy
- William Moomaw papers, 1992 -- 2014; MS216.001; 10.8 Linear Feet 9 boxes; 5 Digital Object(s); 1 Artifact(s)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Vision for the Future, 2004-03-16; MS216-001
    Scope and Contents
    Conference of New England Governors and Eastern Canadian Premiers. "Climate Change in New England and Eastern Canada: Natural Resource Impacts and Adaptation Resources." Suffolk University Law School, Boston, Massachusetts.
  - IEA GHG Reports, 2003-12; MS216-002
    IEA GHG Reports for use in the preparation of IPCC Special Report on CO2 capture and storage.
  - International Conventions - Report Number PH4/16, 2003-03; MS216-003
    International Conventions: Implications for CO2 Storage, Report PH4/16
  - Syllabus of ENVR-E130 Global Climate Change, 2004; MS216-004
    This digital object contains the syllabus for ENVR-E130 Global Climate Change: The Science, Social Impact and Diplomacy of a World Environmental Crisis. This course was taught by William R. Moowmaw and Timothy C. Weiskel at the Harvard University Extension School in Spring 2004.
  - Bio-Syllabus for European Environmental Education, 2001 -- 2002; MS216-005
    Edited by Dr. Agni Vlavianos-Arvanitis
  - Files and publications, 1992 -- 2014; MS216-006; Moomaw, William (Box data_value_missing_efc7dd724cff4c47a366bed424e2d438, Box 1)
  - Files and publications, 1992 -- 2014; MS216-007; Moomaw, William (Box data_value_missing_efc7dd724cff4c47a366bed424e2d438, Box 2)
  - Files and publications, 1992 -- 2014; MS216-008; Moomaw, William (Box data_value_missing_efc7dd724cff4c47a366bed424e2d438, Box 3)
  - Files and publications, 1992 -- 2014; MS216-009; Moomaw, William (Box data_value_missing_8f8e2e9052497a4bbea2dd87dd16c19b, Box 4)
  - Files and publications, 1992 -- 2014; MS216-010; Moomaw, William (Box data_value_missing_d1cf606f205900a2bfcc04d2e5726586, Box 5)
  - Files and publications, 1992 -- 2014; MS216-011; Moomaw, William (Box data_value_missing_d1cf606f205900a2bfcc04d2e5726586, Box 6)
  - Files and publications, 1992 -- 2014; MS216-012; Moomaw, William (Box data_value_missing_d1cf606f205900a2bfcc04d2e5726586, Box 7)
  - Files and publications, 1992 -- 2014; MS216-013; Moomaw, William (Box data_value_missing_d931faf4c04d6c90a5fc5df79560b645, Box 8)
  - Files and publications, 1992 -- 2014; MS216-014; Moomaw, William (Box data_value_missing_d602a55ec15847f07f2a0f6a8d1e239b, Box 9)